<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Raw Syntax]]></title>
  <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-02-22T15:45:29-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://rawsyntax.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Himmelreich]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[eric@rawsyntax.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reload your app with Guard and Pow]]></title>
    <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/reload-your-app-with-guard-and-pow/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-22T15:06:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rawsyntax.com/blog/reload-your-app-with-guard-and-pow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About 6 months ago I started using <a href="http://pow.cx/">Pow</a> for serving
my apps in development mode.  It loads any RACK compatible app, and
allows you to access your projects via the <code>.dev</code> and named symlinks
stored in <code>~/.pow</code> (for example <code>http://my_project.dev</code>).  No need to
specify a port either!</p>

<p>Very shortly afterwards I ran into a problem.  When I'm working on a
Sinatra app, normally I use the
<a href="https://github.com/rtomayko/shotgun">shotgun</a> gem for automatic
reloading. I can't do that when I'm running Pow.  So I dug into Pow's
documentation.</p>

<p>Pow supports passenger-style reloads via these commands:</p>

<pre><code>touch tmp/restart.txt
touch tmp/always_restart.txt
</code></pre>

<p>That's somewhat helpful.  However, remembering to run <code>touch tmp/restart.txt</code> every time I make a change is a pain.  Creating <code>tmp/always_restart.txt</code> reloads every time, but makes the app painfully slow.  I don't need a reload for every css / image / js asset that is fetched.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/guard/guard">Guard</a> to the rescue!  Guard is a
simple tool.  Watch files; run commands on change.  There is already a
<a href="https://github.com/guard/guard-pow">guard-pow</a> gem.  Which touches
<code>tmp/restart.txt</code> on file change.</p>

<p>To use it, add <code>guard-pow</code> to your Gemfile.  Then define a Guardfile
telling it which files to watch.  Your specific files may differ, but
this works for my needs.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/1886987.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>guard 'pow' do
  watch('.rvmrc')
  watch('Gemfile')
  watch('Gemfile.lock')
  watch(%r{^lib/*/.*\.rb$})
  watch(%r{^app/*/.*\.rb$})
end
</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>Finally, run <code>bundle exec guard</code>.  It will print when it restarts pow.
I like this approach because it can be adapted to any RACK compatible
app by changing which files get watched.  Also, it doesn't require you
to change any application specific code; It's only necessary to add
guard to the Gemfile.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Troubleshooting your Emacs Config]]></title>
    <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/troubleshooting-your-emacs-config/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-22T22:26:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rawsyntax.com/blog/troubleshooting-your-emacs-config</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Up to this point my <a href="/blog/categories/learn-emacs">Learn Emacs</a>
series has been all about how to do cool stuff in emacs.  One of my
personal favorites is <a href="/blog/learn-emacs-align-regexp/">align-regexp</a>.
A while back that stopped working for me.  Now I get an error: <code>Wrong type
argument: markerp, 0</code>.  Emacs doesn't always do what I mean.</p>

<h3>First Remove your Config</h3>

<p>Whether you use a single <code>.emacs</code> file or a <code>~/.emacs.d/</code> directory
it is time to remove it.  Personally I keep <code>~/.emacs.d/</code> symlinked to
my <a href="https://github.com/rawsyntax/emacs.d">emacs.d github repo</a> so it iss
quite easy to remove the symlink.  Alternatively you can start emacs
with the <code>--no-init-file</code> option, to skip loading your files. The
rationale for removing your config is simply that it reduces the
number of variables you are dealing with.  Is the problem with your
config or with emacs itself?</p>

<h3>Then Check your Emacs Version</h3>

<p>After I removed my config and tried <code>M-x align-regexp</code> again, I got
the same error.  So its not my config.  If you find you have a problem
with a particular version of emacs <code>M-x emacs-version</code> will tell you
what version you have.  In my case it was</p>

<pre><code>GNU Emacs 24.0.92.1 (x86_64-apple-darwin, NS apple-appkit-1038.36) of 2011-12-02 on bob.porkrind.org
</code></pre>

<p>As I get my emacs builds from
<a href="http://emacsformacosx.com/">EmacsForMacOSX</a> or <code>brew install</code> them
myself.  At this point I'm fairly certain I'm getting the error as a
result of running a nightly build.  A quick google leads me to
<a href="http://lists.gnu.org/archive/html/bug-gnu-emacs/2011-12/msg00266.html">bug#10249: 24.0.92</a>.
I installed a pretest version, and align-regexp works fine like it
used to..  I would prefer to be running the stable version, but I'm using
<a href="https://github.com/technomancy/emacs-starter-kit">emacs-starter-kit</a>
for my config, which requires emacs 24.</p>

<h3>Version your Config</h3>

<p>When functionality like this breaks it is really awesome to have an
emacs configuration that is under version control.  I can walk
backwards through any recent changes to find what is causing breakage.
So if your config isn't already versioned, version it right now.</p>

<p>PS: I'm interested to know any emacs topics you'd like to see a
blogpost on.  I haven't been hacking my emacs config much lately, so
I'm short on ideas for emacs posts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sometimes Side Projects Fail]]></title>
    <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/sometimes-side-projects-fail/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-09T11:44:56-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rawsyntax.com/blog/sometimes-side-projects-fail</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://rawsyntax.com/images/side-projects-fail.jpg" alt="Sometimes Side Projects Fail" class="center"/></p>

<p>I've worked on a few side projects over the years.  Sometimes they've
turned out well, and other times I stopped working on them.  How do
you know when it's time to throw in the towel and when it's time to
push through?</p>

<p>Roughly a year ago a friend and I were working on a bill splitting
system.  It was supposed to solve the problem of splitting bills
between friends.  More specifically, splitting regularly occuring or
one time expenses between roommates.  Rather than worrying about
having cash, or writing a check and waiting for it to cash, we built a
system which piggybacked off of paypal's API to send bill and payment
notifications via email, which would generate a web checkout page
where the debt could be paid online through paypal.</p>

<p>See how long the previous sentence is?  Sounds too complicated already
and I'm the one who built it. The eventual idea was that we would wrap
this in a native client wrapper, so that if you're out to dinner with
your friends you don't have to worry about splitting the bill.  One
person will pick up the entire bill, split it and send bill
notifications via email to all the other people.  Then the others pull
out their phones and enter their paypal accounts and send payment for
their portion of the bill.  The bill can be settled on the spot.</p>

<h3>Not Every Idea is a Hit</h3>

<p>In a perfect world every side-project would be a hit that turns into
a business that generates lots of profit for little work.  In practice
this actually can be quite difficult to pull off.  Furthermore
sometimes those big hits aren't actually big hits when they start.  It
make take a couple of years of work to pull.  But how do you know if
your idea is taking a couple of years to get started or simply not
good at all?  Nobody wants to be a quitter, and worse nobody wants to
quit a good idea that ends up making someone else rich.  But there's
also more to life than money.</p>

<p>After working on this idea for a few hours a week for a couple months
we eventually decided to scrap it.  There really didn't seem to be a simple
way to make money with this idea.  It may have been a useful service,
but there are already similar free services out there for this.  Over
the years, I've grown to have an affinity for ideas that have
monetization strategies that are simple to understand.  In my
experience, the more complicated it is, the less the likelyhood of
actually making money.</p>

<p>Most importantly I wasn't particularly passionate about the idea, and
I didn't like the idea of piggybacking off of Paypal because of their
horrible customer service (I recently had my funds availability
delayed for 3 weeks with no explanation, and I've had an account for 7
years and an ebay account with perfect feedback).  But using another
online payment system made the idea less useful because other peer to
peer payment systems simply aren't as ubiquitous.</p>

<h3>Benefits of Side Projects</h3>

<p>Often the benefits are not monetary in nature.  In the case of this
bill splitting website, I used it at the time to keep up to date with
rails 3 and refresh my skills a little bit.  I was using Merb for most
projects at work at the time. Furthermore, working on small side
projects now and then keeps you familiar with how to start a project
from scratch and increases the breadth of your knowledge.  If its a
small project with just one person working on it, you have to be the
one to do everything (or at least hire the contractors that will do
the part outside your expertise, which is a skill in itself).</p>

<p>The most important thing is to simplify your idea.  Then build the
simplest thing that could possibly work.  Then keep at it and don't be
afraid to re-evaluate your idea.  It doesn't make you a quitter to throw out a project that no longer seems reasonable.</p>

<p>Check out an older post of mine about <a href="/blog/importance-of-side-projects/">side projects</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging on Jekyll: URL Redirects]]></title>
    <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/blogging-on-jekyll-url-redirects/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-29T14:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rawsyntax.com/blog/blogging-on-jekyll-url-redirects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a month ago I migrated my blog from Tumblr to Octopress hosted on github-pages.  I migrated because of Tumblr's slow page loads and frequent downtime.  I picked Octopress because it is built on top of Jekyll, and it comes with a reasonable default stylesheet.  Jekyll is a static site generator, which ensures I can deploy my blog on any old server in the future, and continue to use these same old tools (because I have them, rather than tumblr having them).</p>

<h3>Migrating broke my URL Structure</h3>

<p><img src="http://rawsyntax.com/images/urls_not_found.png" class ="center"/></p>

<p>Running my site through Google's Webmaster Tools showed that many sites are still linking to my old Tumblr blogpost urls.  Tumblr's url structure is another reason I migrated away from it.  I should be in full control of the urls on my blog.  Never the less, I need to support redirects from the old URLs to my new URL structure <code>/blog/:post_title</code>.</p>

<p>However Jekyll is just a static site, so there's no ruby server to handle redirects.  Other Jekyll users deploy to Heroku and use a small Sinatra app to handle redirects, but I feel like that is complicating my simple setup.  If I were on a regular server I could setup an <code>.htaccess</code> file to handle the redirects, but github-pages does not support <code>.htaccess</code>.</p>

<h3>Jekyll Plugins to the Rescue</h3>

<p>One of the great things about Jekyll is its simple plugin system.  On
<a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Plugins">Jekyll's Wiki</a> I
found the
<a href="https://github.com/tsmango/jekyll_alias_generator">Alias Generator</a>.
It allows you to specify aliases on a per blogpost basis, in the YAML
front matter.</p>

<p>This post's YAML is:</p>

<pre><code>---
layout: post
title: "Blogging on Jekyll: URL Redirects"
date: 2011-11-29 14:32
comments: true
categories: ["programming", "blogging"]
alias: [/blog/blogging-on-redirects]
---
</code></pre>

<p>Now when I <code>rake generate</code> my site, the Alias Generator will create
another static html file for this post at
<code>/blog/blogging-on-redirects/index.html</code>:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /&gt;
&lt;meta http-equiv="refresh" content="0;url=/blog/blogging-on-jekyll-url-redirects/" /&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Which will redirect here. Try it: <a href="/blog/blogging-on-redirects">/blog/blogging-on-redirects</a></p>

<p>It was almost that simple.  The Alias Generator actually broke when I
provided some of my old Tumblr urls. However, I
<a href="https://github.com/rawsyntax/jekyll_alias_generator">forked it here</a>
and fixed it so it handles nested aliases properly now.  I also opened
a <a href="https://github.com/tsmango/jekyll_alias_generator/pull/1">pull request</a> to the owner to get this change merged in.</p>

<h3>Jekyll's Strengths</h3>

<p>That experience is Jekyll's strength as a blogging platform.  The
output is so simple any web server can serve it so it doesn't matter
where you deploy to.  Its generation system is open source, hackable,
and has a great plugin system.</p>

<p>But most importantly, even if the Jekyll project implodes tomorrow.  I
still have all my blog's content versioned, and have all the tools
necessary to maintain my blog.  I am not relying on a hosted service
to back up my blog's content, or maintain the tools I edit it with.</p>

<h3>Try Octopress</h3>

<p>If you haven't tried <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> yet, I highly
recommend it.  It's Jekyll based, but it has a decent default
stylesheet, so it's very easy to install and immediately start
blogging.  No programming or tweaking CSS to get in the way of writing content.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Solving the General Case]]></title>
    <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/solving-the-general-case/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-28T16:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rawsyntax.com/blog/solving-the-general-case</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://xkcd.com/974">
<img src="http://rawsyntax.com/images/the_general_problem.png" class ="center"/>
</a></p>

<p>This XKCD comic struck a chord with me.  I feel that it presents a
false dichotomy.  Either miss deadlines to design it right or go wild
west cowboy coding and meet deadlines.  I think there's a middle ground between
those options.  Design it correctly, but deliver less functionality,
and add the rest of the functionality at a later date.  While that's a
simple solution, this comic touches on other related issues.</p>

<h3>Analysis Paralysis</h3>

<p><img src="http://rawsyntax.com/images/analysis-paralysis.jpg" class ="center"/></p>

<p>This affliction is pretty common largely as a result of all the
choices we have nowadays when designing software.  Which language?
Which Framework? How about a
<a href="/blog/the-problem-with-micro-frameworks/">Micro-Framework</a>?  Which
<a href="/blog/categories/learn-emacs/">Text Editor</a>?  Nevermind questions
about how to actually solve the problem at hand.  If a simple flexible
design is not readily coming to mind, I find it helpful to write some
code that implements the very basics of the functionality needed, and
then re-evaluate to figure out a design.  Its a more iterative
approach.  Write a little code. Refactor.  Hopefully a good design
will emerge.  If not try something else.</p>

<h3>Deadline is not a Bad Word</h3>

<p>Growing up my dad would always tell me: "There is no time", but I
didn't understand what he meant until I got a job at 15 years old.
Deadlines are part of life, and furthermore they are not bad.  A
deadline is just a constraint.  Without deadlines we developers could
work on software design forever and never actually get to
implementation!  Deadlines can actually help cure analysis paralysis
by reducing the number of options available to us.  Rewriting the
whole project in python suddenly isn't an option.  Deadlines force
value judgements to be made.</p>

<h3>Why the General Case Takes so Long</h3>

<p>As you begin implementing your perfect design you may find holes.
This is one of the reasons for the shift from waterfall development to
agile (or even just shorter iterative processes).  Once your design is
implemented to 90% you are constrained with all these implementation
details.</p>

<p>To paraphrase Albert Einstein:
<blockquote><p>"At design-time, design and implementation are the same.  At implementation-time, they are not."</p></blockquote></p>

<p>The following quote is about ruby implementation, but it can be applied to any hard general case problem.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Listen, people: Ruby is hard to implement. Oh, it may look easy at a glance, and you can probably get 70, 80, or even 90% of the way pretty quickly. But there's some crazy stuff in that last 10% or 5% that totally blindsides you if you're not looking for it. An early Ruby implementation has not run that last mile of Ruby implementation, and it takes almost as much work to get there as it does to run the first 90%.</p><footer><strong>Charles Nutter</strong><cite><a href='http://blog.headius.com/2009/03/on-benchmarking.html'>blog.headius.com/2009/03/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>When he talks about getting blindsided by that last 10%, that is
potentially a missed deadline.</p>

<h3>Solving the Problem of Solving the General Case</h3>

<p>  Ask yourself if you can live with a 90% solution.  Do you really need to solve the general case?  If 90% is not enough, break the general
case down into many smaller pieces of functionality and many smaller
deadlines.  You may still run into missed deadlines and problems, but
they will have smaller and more predictable impact.  This doesn't
really solve the overall problem of software that takes too long to
develop, but it makes the problems easier to manage.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
