<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: javascript | Raw Syntax]]></title>
  <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-01-04T19:57:21-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://rawsyntax.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Himmelreich]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[eric@rawsyntax.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rewriting github-badges]]></title>
    <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/rewriting-github-badges/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://rawsyntax.com/blog/rewriting-github-badges</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In building <a href="http://rawsyntax.com">rawsyntax</a> I wanted to be able to
link to my <a href="http://github.com/rawsyntax">github profile</a>.</p>

<p>After a little searching I found <a href="http://drnicjavascript.rubyforge.org/github_badge/">drnic's github-badges</a>. It looked great, and I put it on the sidebar of my site. However, when I went to do crossbrowser testing (I develop in firefox, and crossbrowser test before deploying to production) I found that it caused IE[6,7,8] to crash.</p>

<p>This is a big problem. I believe strongly in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progressive_enhancement">graceful degradation / progressive enhancement</a>. It's one thing if IE isn't getting the full experience, but crashing the browser is unacceptable.</p>

<p>At this point, I had to have github-badges on my site. It's simply too cool to
do without. Looking at the <a href="http://drnicjavascript.rubyforge.org/github_badge/">github-badges project site</a> and the source code. I figured it'd be easier to re-implement than to debug the current code (mostly because I'd rather not debug on IE[6,7,8]).</p>

<p>In searching around for other github-badges alternatives, I didn't anything that looked good and actually worked in all browsers. I did happen upon <a href="http://blog.darkhax.com/2010/03/04/make-your-own-badge-with-jquery-and-jaml">darkhax's make-your-own-badge-with-jquery-and-jaml</a> post. Between this and <a href="http://github.com/drnic/github-badges">drnic's github-badges</a> I cobbled together a solution that works in all browsers, and has the same features as drnic's github-badges. It also has user configurable parameters. Check out the code on <a href="http://github.com/rawsyntax/github-badge">github</a>.</p>

<p>UPDATE: I've since removed the github-badges, and added a link to my profile instead</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
