<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blogging | Raw Syntax]]></title>
  <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/categories/blogging/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-31T18:04:37-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://rawsyntax.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Eric Himmelreich]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[eric@rawsyntax.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blogging on Jekyll: URL Redirects]]></title>
    <link href="http://rawsyntax.com/blog/blogging-on-jekyll-url-redirects/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-29T14:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rawsyntax.com/blog/blogging-on-jekyll-url-redirects</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a month ago I migrated my blog from Tumblr to Octopress hosted on github-pages.  I migrated because of Tumblr's slow page loads and frequent downtime.  I picked Octopress because it is built on top of Jekyll, and it comes with a reasonable default stylesheet.  Jekyll is a static site generator, which ensures I can deploy my blog on any old server in the future, and continue to use these same old tools (because I have them, rather than tumblr having them).</p>

<h3>Migrating broke my URL Structure</h3>

<p><img src="http://rawsyntax.com/images/urls_not_found.png" class ="center"/></p>

<p>Running my site through Google's Webmaster Tools showed that many sites are still linking to my old Tumblr blogpost urls.  Tumblr's url structure is another reason I migrated away from it.  I should be in full control of the urls on my blog.  Never the less, I need to support redirects from the old URLs to my new URL structure <code>/blog/:post_title</code>.</p>

<p>However Jekyll is just a static site, so there's no ruby server to handle redirects.  Other Jekyll users deploy to Heroku and use a small Sinatra app to handle redirects, but I feel like that is complicating my simple setup.  If I were on a regular server I could setup an <code>.htaccess</code> file to handle the redirects, but github-pages does not support <code>.htaccess</code>.</p>

<h3>Jekyll Plugins to the Rescue</h3>

<p>One of the great things about Jekyll is its simple plugin system.  On
<a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Plugins">Jekyll's Wiki</a> I
found the
<a href="https://github.com/tsmango/jekyll_alias_generator">Alias Generator</a>.
It allows you to specify aliases on a per blogpost basis, in the YAML
front matter.</p>

<p>This post's YAML is:</p>

<pre><code>---
layout: post
title: "Blogging on Jekyll: URL Redirects"
date: 2011-11-29 14:32
comments: true
categories: ["programming", "blogging"]
alias: [/blog/blogging-on-redirects]
---
</code></pre>

<p>Now when I <code>rake generate</code> my site, the Alias Generator will create
another static html file for this post at
<code>/blog/blogging-on-redirects/index.html</code>:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
&lt;meta http-equiv="content-type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /&gt;
&lt;meta http-equiv="refresh" content="0;url=/blog/blogging-on-jekyll-url-redirects/" /&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Which will redirect here. Try it: <a href="/blog/blogging-on-redirects">/blog/blogging-on-redirects</a></p>

<p>It was almost that simple.  The Alias Generator actually broke when I
provided some of my old Tumblr urls. However, I
<a href="https://github.com/rawsyntax/jekyll_alias_generator">forked it here</a>
and fixed it so it handles nested aliases properly now.  I also opened
a <a href="https://github.com/tsmango/jekyll_alias_generator/pull/1">pull request</a> to the owner to get this change merged in.</p>

<h3>Jekyll's Strengths</h3>

<p>That experience is Jekyll's strength as a blogging platform.  The
output is so simple any web server can serve it so it doesn't matter
where you deploy to.  Its generation system is open source, hackable,
and has a great plugin system.</p>

<p>But most importantly, even if the Jekyll project implodes tomorrow.  I
still have all my blog's content versioned, and have all the tools
necessary to maintain my blog.  I am not relying on a hosted service
to back up my blog's content, or maintain the tools I edit it with.</p>

<h3>Try Octopress</h3>

<p>If you haven't tried <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> yet, I highly
recommend it.  It's Jekyll based, but it has a decent default
stylesheet, so it's very easy to install and immediately start
blogging.  No programming or tweaking CSS to get in the way of writing content.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
